In this video,
we'll look at the concept of a data practitioner and discuss the various roles
and responsibilities of those working in the world of data. Let's begin.
Simply put,
a data practitioner is anyone who works with data In some capacity,
data have become an integral part of our daily lives,
and we are all data users in some way. Whether we're completing digital forms,
managing budgets, using a spreadsheet,
or saving and sharing content on social media platforms,
we're all data practitioners in our own right. In a professional setting.
A data practitioner supports different stages in an organization's data science
process. This involves defining problems and requirements,
collecting and cleaning data, exploratory data analysis,
gathering and reporting insights, building models, and deploying them.
The world of data is diverse and a range of skills is needed to successfully
extract value from data.
Let's explore some common roles of data professionals.
A data strategist is responsible for helping a company to understand how it can
effectively leverage data to drive business value.
They define measurable goals and objectives while working closely with
stakeholders and the data team to develop a plan that aligns a data strategy to
the organization's needs. Once a data strategy is in place,
a data architect uses it to design the blueprints for an organization's data
infrastructure to address its data needs.
This involves defining policies, procedures,
and models for company data collection, storage and access.
Next,
a data engineer actualizes the data architect's blueprints and sets up data
pipelines ensuring the required data are available for other data professionals
in the organization.
Data engineers work closely with data scientists and analysts to understand the
data requirements and design and build the E T L process,
which stands for extract, transform, and Load.
The E T L process involves retrieving data from various sources,
processing it into usable formats,
and finally moving it into a storage destination that can be accessed by others.
A data analyst uses this process data to extract meaningful
insights and trends that can bring value to a business.
They organize and explore the data and then present their analysis, findings,
and insights to stakeholders using reports and dashboards.
Advanced coding skills are not always a requirement for data analysts.
A business intelligence analyst or bi analyst takes on a reporting
role in an organization.
They assess and present on the performance of the organization using dashboards
and key performance indicators or KPIs.
They then turn these insights into actionable results that help to improve the
company's overall performance. For this reason,
they need a deep understanding of the business domain.
A data scientist is a data practitioner who investigates and interprets data to
solve real world problems and support business objectives.
Unlike data analysts and BI analysts,
data scientists use a more technical approach with advanced analytic tools and
techniques such as statistical modeling and machine learning.
They primarily use programming languages and frameworks when working with data.
A machine learning engineer is responsible for building and deploying machine
learning models that learn from data and helping making predictions or
supporting the decisions of an organization.
Machine learning engineers exclusively use programming languages and frameworks
to perform their duties
in the ever evolving world of data organizations'.
Data needs are always changing, and as a result,
specialized data walls that cater to these changing needs are constantly
emerging.
The different stages of the data lifecycle are usually interconnected,
and so data roles commonly overlap. Therefore,
data professionals should try to develop a diverse skillset to enable them to
adapt and collaborate effectively across different roles.
In this video,
we defined the concept of a data practitioner and looked at some of the roles
played by various data professionals in the industry. See you in the next one.